Hello everyone and welcome back
to English pot, my name is Marco.
And my name is Catherine and
today we have a very scary story.
We're actually bringing
you the first of our
advanced media lessons
and what better way
to start it with than a scary
story for Halloween than with.
So what better way to start this advanced
media lesson than with a scary story.
So Halloween is coming
up and advanced media
usually features a
new story or some kind
of story that we can
then kind of break down
and talk about just have
a conversation about
because you're advanced level learners
and you want to have fun with English.
So where is today's spooky story set Marco?
Well, it starts out with
a guy who remembers
something very scary that
happened to him when he was a kid.
Okay and so one of the main characters
in today's story is his great aunt.
That's right.
His great aunt and so basically this is a
family member but it's your father's aunt.
Right.
Your grandmother or
your grandfather's sister.
Right.
So your aunt is your
parent sibling but in
this case we're talking
about one generation
older than that so you
could say great aunt,
great uncle, great
grandfather, great grandmother.
It's like one step back.
So this is usually a
very old person and the
great aunt is definitely an
important character in today's story.
Exactly.
So let's not keep you
in suspense any longer.
Why don't we listen to this scary story
and we'll be right back to talk about it.
Oh no, the lights went out.
Honey, can you lie to candle?
Sure.
What do we do now?
Well, we can just talk,
you know, like we used to.
I know, I'll tell you a scary story.
It happened to me and my
dad when I was a teenager.
I was living with my father at the
time when he received a phone call.
Hello, yes, this is him, I
see, sorry to hear that.
Okay, no problem, I'll be there shortly.
Pack some clothes, Connie,
my great aunt is very ill
and known and the family
wants to take care of her.
We're going to stay at
her house for a few days.
And what aunt, I never
knew you had a great aunt.
Well, the family doesn't talk about
her or get near her for that matter.
Why is that?
Come on, we have to go.
So we arrived at this old house
on the outskirts of our town.
There was almost no one around
and the house had an eerie look to it.
Once inside the house, we
walked to her room and I was
surprised to find my dad's
great aunt in a wheelchair.
Yelling at someone, but
we were alone in the room.
Hi, inner Silla.
This is my son, Tony.
Well, I have you calm.
Why are you here?
Don't you know, it isn't safe.
My time is near.
He's coming for me.
Who is coming for you?
The prince of darkness, the Lord of the
underworld, the tender, the old serpent.
Come on, and Ursula, let's lay you down.
We need to get some rest.
Tony, help me lay her down.
That night, we slept in one of the
twelve rooms of that big old mansion.
The trees outside
seemed to come alive and
their shadows formed
googly shapes on my bed.
All of a sudden, we heard screaming.
Dad, Dad, Dad, something
is attacking ant Ursula.
The door is jammed, stand back.
And Ursula, where are you?
Over here.
But as we approached her, she was lying on
the floor with her hands and feet open like
the Vitruvian man,
breathing heavily with
bloody marks and scratches
on her arms, legs and face.
Remember how I mentioned
that she was in a wheelchair?
My ant had been paralyzed from
the neck down for just over a year.
After this incident,
strange things would
happen in the house,
and my ant would yell and
scream, according to her, warding
off the evil that had come to get her.
As the days passed, she became very
weak and eventually was unable to talk.
My dad had to work during the
day, so I was left to care for her.
When she lost her
voice and laid on her
deathbed, I would hear
her breathe in and out.
So finally, one day, she
breathed it in and never excelled.
At night, I felt relieved that it
was finally over, but it wasn't.
I was so terrified of what I was
hearing, that I didn't sleep all night.
The following morning,
I went to the bathroom,
expecting to find a
mess and everything
torn up, that I found everything
exactly as it was before.
The movers came that
same day, and as we were
cleaning out her drawers
and personal items,
we found strange notebooks with names
and amounts of money written next to them.
We found pictures with people's
faces sewn with black or red string.
And you want to know
what the strangest thing was?
There was a small doll
filled with dead ants,
with a strand of hair
tied around its waist.
And on the doll's face, there was a picture
of me with the numbers, 31, 10, 0, 9.
You know what day it is today?
It's over 31st, 2009.
All right, we're back, so what
do you think, pretty scary?
I got goosebumps, it's a little spooky.
A little scary.
Now what's interesting
about this story, it's
based on a true story, so
that makes it even scary.
No.
Yeah.
Dare I ask?
Does this happen to you?
No, no, I'm not old enough.
This actually happened to a family member
of mine, and that's why I know this story.
So it was kind of told to me when I
was a bit younger and I remembered it.
And well, Halloween is a great
time to remember these things.
And the first time you heard it, it
scared the crap out of me, right?
Oh yeah, for sure.
Actually, the first time I heard it, we
were on an airplane like on October 31st.
Oh wow.
It was very scary.
Well, we've got a lot of
really interesting stuff here.
We're not going to
dwell too long on the
grammar or the vocabulary,
because we assume
that most of you have
understood this, but
there are a couple of things that can be
really difficult even for English speakers.
So the first one is this
phrase, "My time is near.
" My time is near.
So what does that mean exactly?
Well, my time is near,
my end is coming, it means
I'm very old and I'm
probably going to die soon.
So my time, his time, that's when you die.
Okay, so it's always used
in reference to death, right?
In this case, yeah.
So it's used in our friends to death.
And in this case, we
have the aunt who's
talking about herself,
because I'll say his time
is coming, we should
visit him in the hospital.
So it's a kind of softer way of saying
that someone is going to die soon.
Right.
Okay, so my time is
near or his time is near.
All right.
And then something really
interesting in this story as well.
She had many different
names that she called the devil.
So she didn't directly say the devil.
She said the prince
of darkness, prince of
darkness, Lord of the underworld, the
tempter, the tempter and the old serpent.
So these are actually
different ways that historically
have been used to
describe the devil, right?
That's right.
And a lot of them
are biblical, like the old
serpent, you know,
back in the first, the
first pages of the Bible when the
serpent tempts Eve, that's the devil.
And so we hear a lot
of these, especially on
Halloween, these are
great words to use to kind
of diversify and not
say devil, devil, devil.
Right.
Okay.
So apart from those synonyms for the devil,
she also used an interesting phrase towards
the end when she said, I shall
be judged before you can take me.
So judge to judge, this is to
see if something is right or wrong.
But in this case, we talk about
judgment at the end of a person's life.
So that means when you go to the gates of
heaven and there's Saint Peter and he has a
list of the good and the
bad and he says, yes or no.
Right.
And then if you're,
if you're, if you're a
no, you get sent down to
hell here, yes, you go to heaven.
Right.
So she says, I shall be judged.
This means I want my day in court.
I want to, to have my actions
analyzed by Saint Peter, not by you.
Right.
Exactly.
So actually this makes reference to
a lot of beliefs in Christianity, right?
So it's just another,
another aspect of the
story, but of course, but
other religions probably
don't have the same things such as
like the gates of heaven and Saint Peter.
Right.
The system of, the system
of judgment, all right.
So what do you think of the story?
Did you, did you like it?
I really liked it.
I, I thought it was
really spooky and I
thought that it built
up well, but um, I really
I also like the imagery
we talked about,
um, or we haven't
talked about this yet, but
he describes, um, he
describes his great aunt,
the character describes great aunt as
being spread out like the Vitruvian man.
So you have this image
of her arms spread out
and her legs spread out,
you know, that picture
that Da Vinci did of, of a human
being and is like an anatomy
and it's in a circle and that you
can see the legs and the arms.
That's just so really like
a powerful visual image.
Yeah, you can imagine her laying
on the bed in this position, right?
Mm hmm.
Yeah, it is pretty scary.
You have you ever had
any close encounters with
the supernatural or ghosts or
goblins or something like this?
No, personally I've
never had any experiences
like that and I tend to not believe those
stories, but, um, maybe, maybe if this has
happened to someone
I knew I'd be a little bit
more skeptical or less skeptical, but what,
what about like, uh, when they have those
documentaries or those
recordings of strange
voices or appearances,
like these old castles
in England or stuff like
that, what do you think?
I love those shows.
I just watched one and it
was about a haunted house.
There was a woman who
used a Ouija board and
it let a demon out and
the demon possessed
the girl and they
called in a priest and the
priest had to like
exercise the demon from
the little girl and the
house was haunted and
it was hurting people and it
was like possessing people.
Wow, it sounds like a movie.
Yeah, it does, but it
was like a TV show on
Discovery Channel and it
was really, really, really fun.
I don't actually believe that like a spirit
could push someone down the stairs.
I think that you trip
and then you attribute
it to a spirit, but what
about the Ouija board?
That's an interesting tool that many people
say opens up, you know, like portal portals
and dimensions towards hell or
spirits can come out and stuff like that.
Right.
Well, for those of you who don't know, the
Ouija board is a, as a board, like a piece
of cardboard that
has, um, letters on it,
letters and numbers
and so you have this glass
that you hold and
once the spirit comes, it
guides the glass to point out to
names or places and you spell them.
And they're really
popular with like 13 year
old girls who have
these slumber parties and
they use it and we
have to say, you know,
who's she gonna date
and then move and move.
But, um, yeah, I believe in
the power of the human mind.
So I think a lot of times,
even if we're not aware
of it, we're the ones, you
know, manipulating this glass.
We're believing what we want to believe.
Yeah.
But what about you?
Are you superstitious?
Are you, do you believe in ghosts?
I'm not superstitious.
I don't know what to
think about ghosts because
I've actually had a
couple of very strange
encounters with the
supernatural, but I really
wouldn't say, oh
yeah, I believe in ghosts
or I believe there are spirits that haven't
been put to rest or they haven't finished
business, you know, like in
Casper or something like that.
Yeah.
Since we were having dinner with my family
and in a house where we used to live and it
was a very old house and
we had a glass of water
on the table and all
of a sudden it started
to move and to rotate
across the table, the
center of the table and we all
saw it and no one was touching it.
So we all were pretty confused and nervous
and then just kind of burst out in nervous
laughter and we didn't really know what to
make of it, but it was very strange because
it moved a good amount, it
was like half of the table and
it was spinning at the same
time so it was very strange.
So things like this and
in general Hispanic or
Latin American culture
are very superstitious.
They have a lot of
beliefs and like magic or
some people still say
are reluctant to give
out a picture for example because
of something like this in the story.
We said you shouldn't
give out pictures to
boyfriends or girlfriends
or anyone because if
you break up or
something is to happen then
they could do something with
that picture and maybe hurt you.
Really.
So this idea that you have
a likeness, like a picture
or a doll or something,
can you talk about that?
Because I don't really
know anything about it.
Having that means that you're able to
like do something to that very person?
Yeah.
Like not necessarily
like a voodoo doll, right?
Or you see that you can put pins
in it and then it would hurt someone.
But people believe
that pictures for example
they capture your
image and so if somebody
has it and wants to do
harm or black magic then
they can use that as an
instrument to get into you.
Okay.
The same as pieces of clothing or
the same as hair and things like this.
So that's why there are the shamans or the
Indian witch doctors who do cleansing like
this and people still
actually go to them,
people in the city still
believe in these things
and they'll go to a
shaman and get themselves
cleanse because they
believe that they're
luck.
They have really bad
luck or they've been very,
very sick for a long time and
doctors can't figure out what it is.
They think it's because someone
has cast a spell on them or is
doing some black magic to them
and they need to get it cleansed.
Oh wow.
So yeah, it's really, really common.
But it's all part of
the folklore and the
heritage of the countries
and, you know, it's
actually very, very
interesting and some
things are just really
out there, really weird.
Yeah.
Well, a lot of it I think
comes from indigenous
beliefs mixing with
Catholicism too, right?
Yeah.
Because a lot of South
American countries and
Latin American countries
are very Catholic.
But it's, they get
kind of melded these
traditions with indigenous
beliefs and then you
have these crazy rituals
and like we actually
have a belief and
it's very true that, you
know, when somebody
is completely in love with
this girl and this
girl is like maybe, you
know, not very nice
or not very nice to that
guy, but he's still
completely into her.
Right.
So there's this word
that we say that that
he's been like under
weird or something like
that.
The reason behind
this is that one of these
rituals that I talked
about is that the girl
would make tea, right,
would take a tea pot and
in it would put her
underpants, use underpants
to make the tea water and
then would serve it to the guy.
So the moment that
he drank it, this was like
a magic potion and then he would
continuously be in love with her.
Oh, yeah.
It's very strange.
That's gross.
Did people actually do that?
No.
It's not something that you do now.
It's something that has
that people knew about
that used to be done
way, way, way before.
Okay.
So people now, it's
part of the language
where you say that someone
has been like under weird or sad.
She cast a spell and
maybe what we would say.
So things like this, that of course, aren't
really done anymore, but still people make
reference to it because we know it from our
history that that it's been done before.
How cool.
Well, really curious to
know if our users have
any similar stories or have any scary
stories they want to tell that they do.
I'm sure they do.
And this advanced
media lesson is a great
place for you to do that
because we expect that
a lot of advanced level
learners are going to
be listening to it and practicing
your writing is really important.
So we hope that you'll put
some comments on this lesson
and of course, ask us as
many questions as you want.
All right.
So we'll see you guys there
and have a happy Halloween.
Happy Halloween.
Bye.
(upbeat music)